Guide to the Joseph B. Danzansky papers, 1968-1989 MS2059
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Joseph B. Danzansky papers
1968-1989
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Danzansky, Joseph B.
MS2059
3.5 Linear Feet
Collection includes speeches, photographs, biographical sketches, videotapes, fundraising documents, membership lists, symposium materials, correspondence, publications, resolutions, a survey, and reports. The material dates from 1968-89. The collection documents the professional life of Joseph Danzansky, particularly during his time as president of Giant Food Inc., his involvement in D.C. development, both economically and socially
Restrictions on Access
This collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Danzansky Papers were donated to the Gelman Library Special Collections Department in 1991.
Historical or Biographical Note
Joseph B. Danzansky (1914-1979) received his bachelor of arts, bachelor of laws and juris doctorate degrees from George Washington University. In 1941, Danzansky opened the law firm of Danzansky & Dickey where he practiced until he was elected president of Giant Food Inc. in 1964. In 1977, he became Chairman of the Board of Giant and upon his resignation, in 1978, became chairman of the Board of the National Bank of Washington. Extremely active in the DC community throughout his life, Danzansky was, president (1971, 1976) of the Metropolitan Washington Board of Trade, member of the George Washington Board of Trustees (1969-72), chairman of: the Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corporation (1979), the Business Resource Center (1973-74), and the Mayor's Economic Development Committee of the D.C. (1963-74), as well as a member of many other organizations. His positive impact on the DC community was immediately evident as numerous organizations and individuals took steps to commemorate his memory. The Danzansky Commemorative Committee was formed and it succeeded in honoring the memory of Danzansky by dedicating an amphitheatre at the GW Law School, funding a symposium on Conflict Resolution at GWU, and placing a commemorative plaque on Pennsylvania Avenue.
Danzansky was born on May 16, 1914 in Washington, DC. He married Ethel E. Gelfand and they had two sons, Stephen I. Danzansky and Richard F. Danzansky. Joseph Danzansky died on November 8, 1979.
Collection Scope and Content
The materials in this collection include speeches, photographs, biographical sketches, videotapes, fundraising documents, membership lists, symposium materials, correspondence, publications, resolutions, a survey, and reports. The material dates from 1968-89. The collection documents the professional life of Joseph Danzansky, particularly during his time as president of Giant Food Inc., his involvement in D.C. development, both economically and socially, the impact of his death upon the community, and the various means by which his memory was honored. The collection materials were compiled by the combined efforts of Mrs. Ethel Danzansky, Mr. Stephen I. Danzansky, Mr. Barry F. Scher, Mr. Oral Suer, Mr. M. J. Brodie, and Mr. Paul S. Forbes.
Collection Organization
Organized into seven series: Personal information, Professional and volunteer associations, Speeches, statements and testimony, Photographs, Post-humus documentation, Audio-visual materials, and Oversized documents.
Washington (D.C.) -- History; Economic development; Videotapes; Photographs; George Washington University--Alumni and alumnae; Giant (Firm); Danzansky, Joseph B.
- Personal information, 1971-1980; MS2059 Series 1; 0.25 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains biographical sketches of Joseph Danzansky as well as miscellaneous memos and awards given and received by him. The material dates from 1971-80.
  - Biographical Sketch, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Awards-given and received, 1971-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Memos, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Professional and volunteer associations, 1968-1989; MS2059 Series 2; 1 Linear feet
  This series contains reports, blueprints, correspondence, memos, annual reports, and other documents related to Danzansky's professional life. The material dates from 1968-89. The subjects of these records include Giant Food, the company's involvement in the Central City Market crisis and the Blue Laws controversy. The records also document Danzansky's time as Chairman of the National Bank of Washington. Danzansky's volunteer involvement related to D.C. development included organizations such as Metropolitan Business Resource Center, The Metropolitan Washington Board of Trade, The United Way, the Mayor's Economic Development Committee, and the Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corporation.
  - Chesapeake and Potomac Telephone Co., undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Metropolitan Business Resource Center, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Metropolitan Washington Board of Trade, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The National Bank of Washington, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The United Way, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - United Way, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Giant Food Incorporated, Corporate organization, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Giant Food Incorporated, Fiscal Information, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Giant Food Incorporated, Publications, 1967-1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Giant Food Incorporated, Giant WE News, 1967-1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Giant Food Incorporated, Meat Prices, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Central City Markets, General Information, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Central City Markets, Blueprint for Giant Store on "O" St, 1976 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Central City Markets, Proposal for the Development of Neighborhood Shopping Sited in DC, Drafts, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Central City Markets, Inner-City Food Distribution Dale L. Anderson, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Central City Markets, Exodus of Food Chain Stores Report March, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Central City Markets, Competition and Technology D I Padberg, 1976 June 09 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Central City Markets, Food Retailing, Dr. Kenneth Farrell (06/09/1976), 1966-1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Central City Markets, City Eco-Culture and the Supermarket Dr. Gordon Bloom, 1976 June 09 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Central City Markets, Factors Contributing to the Exodus of Food Chains from the Inner-City Donals R. Marian April 18-19, 1977 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Central City Markets, A Positive Approach to the Problem of Inner Cityfood Distribution Dr. Gordon F. Bloom April 18-19, 1977 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Central City Markets, Structure of Food Retailing in Central Cities... G Featser, G Grimell and R Parks April 18-19, 1977 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Blue Laws, Maryland, 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Virginia, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Mayor's Economic Development Committee, Amended Order of Establishment and Grant Conditions, 1970 February 17 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Mayor's Economic Development Committee, Grant Extension Application, 1972 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Mayor's Economic Development Committee, General Information, 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Mayor's Economic Development Committee, Projects Report, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Mayor's Economic Development Committee, Survey of Business in Washington, DC Summer, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mayor's Economic Development Committee, Activities Report, 1973 February 01-1974 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mayor's Economic Development Committee, Overall Development Program General Information, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mayor's Economic Development Committee, Overall Development Program for DC, 1969 Report (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Mayor's Economic Development Committee, Overall Development Program for DC, Report, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Overall Development Program for DC, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - DC Development Bank, 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corporation, Appointment of Danzansky as chairman, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corporation, The Pennsylvania Plan, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corporation, Annual Reports, 1983-1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corporation, Promotional Materials and Newspaper Publications, 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Speeches, statements and testimony, 1968-1976; MS2059 Series 3; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series is composed of the transcripts of speeches given by Joseph Danzansky between 1968-78.
  - Speeches, statements and testimony, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Speeches, statements and testimony, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Speeches, statements and testimony, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Speeches, statements and testimony, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Speeches, statements and testimony, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Speeches, statements, and testimony, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Esther Peterson speeches [1/3], 1970 September - 1972 November 29; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Esther Peterson speeches [2/3], 1970 September - 1972 November 29; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Esther Peterson speeches [3/3], 1970 September - 1972 November 29; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Photographs, 1972-1976; MS2059 Series 4; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series contains photographs. These photographs came from photograph albums and cover Danzansky's activities. The albums date from 1972-76.
  - Album 1 Danzansky, Honoree at NCCJ Brotherhood Citation Diner, 1972 February 15 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Album 2 Danzansky, president of the Metropolitan Board of Trade, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Album 3 Bicentennial Celebration, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Album 4, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Album 5, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Post-humous materials, 1979-1992; MS2059 Series 5; 0.5 Linear feet
  The series contains a memorial service program, correspondence, membership lists, publications, and resolutions. These records are dated 1979-92. These records documents the impact of Danzansky's death upon the D.C. community and the work of the Joseph B. Danzansky Commemoration Committee including the naming of the Joseph B. Danzansky Amphitheater at The George Washington University Law School. There is also some information about the National Bank of Washington scandal dated 1980-81.
  - Memorial Service, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Publications - Obituaries and Commemorative Statements, 1979-1986 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Resolutions and personal statements in memory of Danzansky, 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Danzansky Soccer League, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - National Bank of Washington Scandal, 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Joseph B Danzansky Commemoration Committee, Meeting Documentation, 1979-1991 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Joseph B Danzansky Commemoration Committee, Membership Lists, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Joseph B Danzansky Commemoration Committee, Volunteers, 1979-1990 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Joseph B Danzansky Commemoration Fund, 1979-1981 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Joseph B Danzansky Commemoration Committee, Community Foundation, 1979-1982 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Joseph B Danzansky Commemoration Committee, Fundraising Events, 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Joseph B Danzansky Commemoration Committee, Danzansky Memorial, 1979-1991 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Joseph B Danzansky Commemoration Committee, Publications - Danzansky Memorial, 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Joseph B Danzansky Commemoration Committee, Memorial Dedication Ceremony, 1991 October 23 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Joseph B Danzansky Commemoration Committee, Memorial Film, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Joseph B Danzansky Commemoration Committee, Conflict Resolution Symposium at George Washington University, 1980 October 15 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Joseph B Danzansky Commemoration Committee, Joseph B Danzansky Amphitheater - GW Law School, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Joseph B Danzansky Commemoration Committee, Washington Civic Festival/Danzansky Commemoration Festival, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Joseph B Danzansky Commemoration Committee, Correspondence, 1979-1990 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Audio-visual materials, undated; MS2059 Series 6; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series is composed of eight U-matic reels, one Betamax, and one VHS. The visual picture on the majority of the materials is distorted to various degrees although the audio on all is clear. Most of the items are not dated, but the Danzansky Memorial Dedication Ceremony took place on October 23, 1991. Other tapes are also remembrances of Danzansky.
  - It's Academic - Danzansky segment, undated (Box 7, Videocassette 1)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    1 videocassette of 1 (U-matic): sd., col., 3/4 in.
  - Channel 4 - air check on Giant Food story, undated (Box 7, Videocassette 2)
  - Danzansky's Death U-matic, undated (Box 7, Videocassette 3)
  - Channel 20 Editorial - Tribute to Joe Danzansky Betamax, undated (Box 7, Videocassette 4)
    1 videocassette (U-matic) of 1: sd., col., 3/4 in.
  - Danzansky Memorial Dedication Ceremony, 1991 October 23 (Box 7, Videocassette 5)
    1 videocassette of 1 (VHS) (30 min.): sd., col., 1/2 in.
  - "The Making of an Intern" (5 min.) and "A Little More Equal" (6:30 min.), undated (Box 7, Videocassette 6)
    1 videocassette of 1
  - Untitled, undated (Box 7, Videocassette 7)
    1 videocassette of 1 (U-matic)
  - Tribute to Joseph B Danzansky, undated (Box 8, Videocassette 1)
    1 videocassette of 1 (U-matic) (10:30 min.): sd., col., 3/4 in.
  - F. M. I. Award Ceremony, undated (Box 8, Videocassette 2)
    1 videocassette of 1 (U-matic) (5:00 min.): sd., col., 3/4 in.
  - Remembering Danzansky, undated (Box 8, Videocassette 3)
    1 videocassette of 1 (U-matic) (2:30 min.): sd., col., 3/4 in.
  - Channel 20 - Editorial Tribute to Joe Danzansky, undated (Box 8, Videocassette 4)
    1 videocassette of 1 (U-matic) (1:30 min.): sd., col., 3/4 in.
- Oversized documents, undated; MS2059 Series 7; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series contains an award, framed poem, bound volume, framed certificate, and plaque. Not all the items are dated, but the ones that are dated are from 1971.
  - Award given in appreciation of Loyal Support to Joseph Danzansky by the George Washington University Sesquicentennial Club, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Framed poem entitled "IF" adapted by Danzansky, 1971 December 15 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Bound edition of the Board of Trade News, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Framed certificate presented to Danzansky for the "IF" Award December, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Plaque given to Danzansky on behalf of the United Way, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)